<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>



<document>

  <properties>
    <title>How to use the SBB WebService</title>
    <author email="maierf@student.ethz.ch">Franz Maier</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section>
      <p>
        To use the SBB WebService on the mobile device, first deploy the SBB midlet
        on the mobile device as described in <i>How to setup the mobile device</i>.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        By touching the shortcut on the screen you can start the SBB Midlet. After launching
        the application you get an input screen where you can type in your search criteria.
      </p>
      <p>
	      <img width="250" height="330" src="../images/jadabs-ws_screenshot_01.gif"/>
      </p>

      <p>
        The main menu contains the menu items "Send", "Result", "Configuration", "Log" and "Exit".
        To search for a certain connection you have to type in the departure station and the station
        where to arrive, as well as the date and time, when to travel. Click the "Send" button to
        request a connection for the given data.
      </p>
      <p>
        <img width="250" height="330" src="../images/jadabs-ws_screenshot_02.gif"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        An alert will show that the request was successfully forwarded to the next proxy. By clicking
        "OK" you will get back to the initial window where you put in the data. Click the "Result"
        button and you get either a selection for ambiguous stations you typed in or a list with 4
        connections is shown on the screen.
      </p>
      <p>
	      <img width="250" height="330" src="../images/jadabs-ws_screenshot_03.gif"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        If the result shows a list with a selection for different stations, you have to choose
        a unique station and send the request again.
      </p>
      <p>
      	<img width="250" height="330" src="../images/jadabs-ws_screenshot_04.gif"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        When a list with 4 connections is displayed on the screen, you can choose one of them and
        click the "send" button again.
      </p>
      <p>
      	<img width="250" height="330" src="../images/jadabs-ws_screenshot_05.gif"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        The result will show the details for one connection, i.e. the departure station, the station
        to arrive, the departure and arrival time, the platforms, a travel with description and a comment.
      </p>
      <p>
      	<img width="250" height="330" src="../images/jadabs-ws_screenshot_06.gif"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        If you go back to the result list with 4 connections shown on the display, you can either save this
        connections by clicking the save button (not yet implemented) or go back to the initial query form.
      </p>
      <p>
      	<img width="250" height="330" src="../images/jadabs-ws_screenshot_07.gif"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        The main menu associated with the initial window contains two other possibilities for interaction:
        You can select the "Log" menu item and you will see the output generated by the logger of the
        application. if you select "Configuration" a window with copyright info will be displayed and you
        additionally have the possibility to choose a connection type, either HTTP or BT (at the moment
        only BT is implemented).
      </p>
      <p>
      	<img width="250" height="330" src="../images/jadabs-ws_screenshot_08.gif"/>
      </p>
      
    </section>

  </body>

</document>