<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>


<document>

  <properties>
    <title>How to setup the proxy</title>
    <author email="maierf@student.ethz.ch">Franz Maier</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section>
      <p>
        For setting up the proxy, process the following steps:
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="1. Install and configure a Linux operating system.">
        <p>
          As a preconditon to run all kind of software needed on the proxy
          you have to setup a suitable Linux distribution as the operating
          system of the computer that works as your proxy. For detailed
          information please see the installation instructions provided by
          the vendor of your operating system.
        </p>
    </section>

    <section name="2. Install and configure BlueZ">

        <p>
          BlueZ the official Bluetooth stack for Linux has to be installed as
          the next step of the proxy setup process. A detailed description
          how to do this can be found in the diploma thesis of Daniel Käppeli
          (Daniel Käppeli, DA, 2004 p.41 - p.47)
        </p>
    </section>

    <section name="3. Install and configure Impronto Developer Kit for Linux.">

        <p>
          For a working Bluetooth communication some additional libraries have to be
          installed on you computer. A detailed description how to install them
          can also be found within the work done by Daniel Käppeli (Daniel Käppeli,
          DA, 2004 p.51 - p. 55)
        </p>
    </section>

    <section name="4. Install and start the Jadabs framework on your proxy.">

        <p>
          The Jadabs framework as well as further bundles which are used for
          the communication with the SBB Midlet have to be installed on your
          system. Checkout (if possible) the latest stable release from CVS
          and place it together with some other bundles under ~/.maven/repository/${bundle.name}/jars
        </p>
        <p>
          Create a folder where to checkout the 'jadabs-ws' project from CVS
          and checkout the complete project from CVS.
          Change to the folder where you checked out the project and go to
          "jadabs-ws/bundles/sbbproxy". There you will find 'start.sh', 'init.xargs'
          and 'log4j.properties' as well as some other project related files.
          To start the proxy run 'start.sh' and the Jadabs framework will come
          up on your proxy.
        </p>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>