<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>



<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Messenger Overview</title>
    <author email="jannethm@student.ethz.ch">Janneth Malibago</author>
  </properties>
  
  <body>
  
  <section name="How to use the Messenger">
  
  	<ol>
	  	<li>
			<p>
			    Create a new account with the 
			    <a href="http://wlab.ethz.ch:8080/jadabs-im/">Webapplication</a> and define how you
			    want to be notified in case somebody sends you an instant message while
			    you are being offline.
		    </p>
		    
			<p>
			    You can choose between the following options:
			    <ul>
			    	<li>
			    		email only
			    	</li>
			    	<li>
			    		mobile phone only
			    	</li>
			    	<li>
			    		email and mobile phone
			    	</li>				    	
			    </ul>
		    </p>
		</li>       
		
		<li>
			<p>
				Start the <a href="../proxy.html">SIP Proxy</a>,
			</p>
		</li>
		
		<li>
			<p>
				Start the Messenger application 
				(see also the the <a href="../howto/setup.html">setup informations</a>)
			</p>
		</li>
  	
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				Enter your SIP settings into the <code>Settings</code> panel and save the changes.
  			</p>
  			
  			<p>
  				<img src="../images/settings.jpg"/>
  			</p>
  			
  			<p>
				On the laptop the default SIP settings are defined in <code>imSettings.properties</code>, 
				on the IPAQ they are defined in <code>init-ppcj9.xargs</code> respectively. 
				For the mobile phone the default SIP settings need to be defined as attributes in <code>midlet.xml</code>
			</p>
  		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				In the <code>Buddies</code> panel you will see all the SIP buddies which are loaded from the 
  				<code>buddy.list</code> file.
  				
  				Buddies who are online are preceded by a green status icon, those who are offline by a red status icon.
  				If there is no status icon this means, that the status of the corresponding buddy is not known.
			</p>

			<p>
				<img src="../images/buddies.jpg"/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				You can add new buddies and their properties will be saved in <code>buddy.list</code> from where you can load them again
				the next time you start the Messenger.
				(This option is not yet implemented for the mobile phone)
			</p>			
		</li>
		
		<li>
			<p>
				After connecting you can see all JXME peers who are online in the <code>Neighbours</code> panel.
				The JXME peers are preceded by a blue status icon to indicate that they belong to the peer to peer
				neighbourhood.
			</p>
			<p>
				<img src="../images/neighbours.jpg"/>
			</p>
		</li>
  		<li>
  			<p>
  				When you want to send a message to one of your buddies or neighbours just go to the <code>Message</code> panel,
  				select a receiver, type your message and send it.
  			</p>
			<p>
				<img src="../images/messages.jpg"/>
			</p>
			<p>
				You can only send messages to to peers who are online or, in the case of SIP buddies, when the buddy registered with the SIP proxy.
				A peer who is online will receive the message immediately. When a buddy is offline he will
				be notified by email or sms or both, according to his preferences set in the
				<a href="http://wlab.ethz.ch:8080/jadabs-im/">Webapplication</a>.
			</p>			
		</li>		
  	</ol>

  	
	

	
  </section>



  </body>

</document>