<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <author email="caduffo@student.ethz.ch">Otmar Caduff</author>
  </properties>

	<body>
	    
  	<section name="Overview">
  		<p>
  			This section gives a short overview of the methods used.
  		</p>
		<subsection name="Digital signatures">
			<p>
				With digital sigantures, it is possible to sign data similiar to signing
				paper documents with your own signature. Thus, it can state as a proof that
				the data was signed by the person holding the signature and it is not
				possible for another person to forge the signature. Furthermore, once data
				was signed, it can not be altered and its signature can not be used for
				other data.
			</p>
			<p>
				Data is digitally signed using asymetric encryption algorithms (e.g. DSA,
				RSA): the signer encrypts the data (or its digest) to be signed using his private
				key. The resulting encrypted data represents the digital signature and can be
				verified with the corresponding public key.
			</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Digital certificates">
			<p>
				Digital certificates ensure that a public key belongs to the entity it pretends
				to be. Basically, a certificate represents a public key signed by a trusted authority,
				i.e. the signature of a certificate can be verified with a public key that
				can be considered as trusted. X.509 is aknown as the most important standard for
				digital certificates.
			</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Digests">
			<p>
				Encryption of data using established security algorithms is cpu-intensive, thus
				it is important to keep the data to be encrypted as small as possible. For this
				reason, a digest - similiar to a fingerprint of a person - is computed and instead
				of the whole data, just the digest is encrypted. Digests are computed using
				cryptographic hash functions that ensure certain security properties. For
				example, computing different data that yields the digest of given data is
				hardly possible with reasonable computing resources. SHA-1 is an example of a
				cryptographic hash function.
			</p>
		</subsection>
	</section>
	</body>
</document>
