<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Properties</title>
    <author email="caduffo@student.ethz.ch">Otmar Caduff</author>
  </properties>

	<body>
	    
  	<section name="Properties for the Maven-OSGi Plugin">
		<table>
          <tr><th>property</th><th>default value</th><th>description</th></tr>
          <tr>
          	<td><code>osgi.maven.security.digestGenerationAlgorithm</code></td>
          	<td><code>-</code></td>
          	<td>
          		If a digest generation algorithm is given, the digest of
          		the bundle is computed and emitted to the <code>.obr</code> file.
          		This property is optional, becuase most algorithms used to sign
          		compute a digest by themselves.
          	</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
          	<td><code>osgi.maven.security.provider</code></td>
          	<td><code>-</code></td>
          	<td>
          		The class name of the security provider to be installed and
          		added to the already available providers. It must be a subclass
          		of <code>java.security.Provider</code>. If you want to use this
          		option, make sure that the classes are available in the classpath.
          		This property is also optional.
          	</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
          	<td><code>osgi.maven.security.keystoreLocation</code></td>
          	<td><code>{user.home}/.keystore</code></td>
          	<td>
          		The location of the file containing the keystore information.
          		A keystore is basically a set of certificates and keys.
          	</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
          	<td><code>osgi.maven.security.keystoreType</code></td>
          	<td>
          		The default keystore type as specified in the Java security
          		properties file or <code>JKS</code> if no such property exists.
          	</td>
          	<td>
          		The type of the keystore. Possible values would be
          		<code>JKS</code> or <code>PKCS12</code>.
          	</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
          	<td><code>osgi.maven.security.keystoreAlias</code></td>
          	<td><code>maven-osgi</code></td>
          	<td>
          		The alias that identifies the certificate and private key
          		used to sign the bundles.
          	</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
          	<td><code>osgi.maven.security.keyPassword</code></td>
          	<td><code>osgi-pwd</code></td>
          	<td>
          		The password needed to access the private key in the keystore.
          		It's not recommended to add this property to a file you check
          		in a repository. You can for example set this property when
          		calling maven, e.g. <code>maven
          		-Dosgi.maven.security.keyPassword={your password}</code>.
          	</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
          	<td><code>osgi.maven.security.showPublicKey</code></td>
          	<td><code>-</code></td>
          	<td>
          		If this property is set to true, a base64 encoded version of the
          		public key is printed on the screen when a bundle is signed.
          		Might be helpful for debugging.
          	</td>
          </tr>
      </table>
	</section>
	<section name="Properties for the Jadabs peers">
		<table>
          <tr><th>property</th><th>default value</th><th>description</th></tr>
          <tr>
          	<td><code>ch.ethz.jadabs.bundlesecurity.jaruuid</code></td>
          	<td><code>-</code></td>
          	<td>
          		The uuid of the bundle containing the security enhancement.
          		It must implement the
          		<code>ch.ethz.jadabs.bundleLoader.api.BundleSecurity</code>
          		interface. If this property is not set, the bundle loader will try
          		to verify the signature with a minimal implementation included in
          		the bundle loader itself.
          	</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
          	<td><code>ch.ethz.jadabs.bundlesecurity.ignoresecurity</code></td>
          	<td><code>-</code></td>
          	<td>
          		If this property is set to true, downloaded bundles will be
          		installed and run with no security checks. This property is
          		optional.
          	</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
          	<td><code>ch.ethz.jadabs.bundlesecurity.publickey</code></td>
          	<td><code>-</code></td>
          	<td>
          		A base64 representation of the <code>subjectPublicKey</code>
          		information of the certificate used to verify the signature.
          		Only needed if the bundle loader has to check the signature by
          		itself, i.e. when no bundlesecurity bundle was loaded and
          		the security enhancements are enabled.
          	</td>
          </tr>
		</table>
	</section>
	</body>
</document>
