<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!-- 
/* This is the Documentation of the SMTP-Gateway component. 
 * Rene Mueller, 2004-10-15
 * Semester work: JXME-Bluetooth for a Mobile Phone (J2ME/CLDC)
 */
 -->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Smart Messenger MIDlet application</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Smart Messenger MIDlet application">
	<p>
      The Smart Messenger MIDlet application can be used to send sort 
      message from a mobile phone. But in contrast to the native
      messaging application that can be used on mobile phones to 
      sending short messages the Smart Messenger does not always 
      use the expensive GSM network to send the messages. If the 
      mobile device is brought into the vicinity of a infrastructure 
      node (such as a notebook) which is also equipped with a Bluetooth interface and 
      has the SMTP-Gateway Service installed it sends the short message
      over a preconfigured SMTP-SMS-Gateway (such as <code>sms.switch.ch</code>). 
      In many cases this SMTP-SMS-Gateway can be used for free (at least for 
      a certain number of messages per month/day). </p>
    <p>The Smart Messenger is basically only a small MIDlet application that 
		 provides a simple GUI where the user can enter the phone number the 
       short message is to be sent to and the message text itself. The Smart 
       Messenger directly uses the 
	    <a href="../smsgateway/index.html">SMS-Gateway Service</a>
       that transparently forwards the messages either over WMA or over the 
       SMTP-SMS-Gateway. The Smart Messenger Application does not implement any
       logic for delivering the short messages. This logic is encapsulated in the 
  	    SMS-Gateway Service. Thus the name <i>Smart Messenger</i> is somewhat 
       misleading. In fact the Smart Messenger actually rather dump, it is the 
       SMS-Gateway Service component that has the smart logic implemented. </p>
       
    <p>An overview of a possible setup for the Smart Messenger is shown below:</p>
    
		<img src="images/smartmessengeroverview.jpg"/>
	<p>See the documentation of the <a href="../smsgateway/index.html">SMS-Gateway Service</a>
      for more details about the architecture and implementation of sub system that 
      is responsible for the sending of the short messages.       
	</p>
   
   <p>In the sequel the configuration properties of the Smart Messenger are described. Then
      a short manual is presented that illustrates how the Smart Messenger can be used 
      together with a infrastructure node. </p>

	<subsection name="Configuration of the MIDlet">
      <p>The Smart Message Application uses six different bundle components. 
         Even though the messenger application itself is very simple the components
         it uses are very complex. They are not yet able to automatically
         deduce the correct configuration, i.e. which the SMTP-SMS-Gateway
         has to be used, have to be configured according to the
         environment setting.                
      </p>
      <p>The Smart Messenger MIDlet-suite can be customized by the following 
         application properties:         
      </p>
      
	<table>
   	<tr>
         <th>Application Property Key</th> <th>Value (example)</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
         <td><code>ch.ethz.jadabs.jxme.hostname</code></td>
         <td><code>Buggy Phone</code></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
         <td><code>ch.ethz.jadabs.jxme.bt.rendezvouspeer</code></td>
         <td><code>false</code></td>         
      </tr>
      <tr>
         <td><code>ch.ethz.jadabs.mservices.smsgateway.emailsuffix</code></td>
         <td><code>sms.switch.ch</code></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
         <td><code>ch.ethz.jadabs.mservices.smsgateway.senderaddress</code></td>
         <td><code>torvalds@transmeta.com</code></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
         <td><code>log4j.priority</code></td>
         <td><code>DEBUG</code></td>
      </tr>
   </table>

	<p>
      <code>ch.ethz.jadabs.jxme.hostname</code> sets the JXME peername that is used 
      for this device. This is not used on J2SE since JXME is 
      able to obtain the peername from the name of the local host using
      <code>InteAddress.getLocalHost().getHostName()</code>. However
      <code>InetAddress</code> is not available on CLDC/MIDP. Thus 
      the peer name has to be specified explicitly.      
	</p>
   
   <p>
      <code>ch.ethz.jadabs.jxme.bt.rendezvouspeer</code> sets the 
      operation mode for JXME BT Transport. Since the SMS-Gateway will connect to 
      an infrastructure node which is most probably a rather 
      powerful device (e.g. a notebook) which is also equipped with a fixed 
      network interface the infrastructure node will be operated as 
      <i>rendez-vous peer</i>. Therefore the device running the 
      Smart Messenger application has to be configured as <i>normal peer</i>.       
   </p>
   
   <p>
      <code>ch.ethz.jadabs.mservices.smsgateway.emailsuffix</code> sets the
      email suffix that is appended to the phone number string 
      to obtain the email address used for contacting the SMTP-SMS-Gateway. 
      (e.g. for sending a short message to 0791234567 the email will sent to
      07912345678@sms.switch.ch,
   </p>
   
   <p>
      <code>ch.ethz.jadabs.mservices.smsgateway.senderaddress</code> sets the
      sender address that the email to the SMTP-SMS Gateway is sent from.
      <b>Note</b> that since most SMTP server do not allow relaying, the 
      sender address cannot be chosen randomly, it must lie in the 
      domain served by the SMTP server.
   </p>
   
   <p>
      <code>log4j.priority</code> determines the granularity 
      (in Apache's Log4J the term Priority is used) level of the Logger. 
      Possible values are <code>DEBUG</code>, <code>INFO</code>, <code>WARN</code>,
     <code>ERROR</code> and <code>FATAL</code>.
   </p>
   
   <p>These properties can be edited in the JAD file 
      (<code>smartmessenger.jad</code>) with a text editor without 
      recompiling or rebuilding the MIDlet-suite. Java Descriptor example: </p>
      
<source>MIDlet-Jar-URL: smartmessenger.jar
MIDlet-Jar-Size: 78705
MIDlet-Name: Smart Messenger
MIDlet-Vendor: Andreas Frei, Rene Mueller, ETH Zurich
MIDlet-Version: 1.0.0
MIDlet-1: Smart Messenger, , ch.ethz.jadabs.smartmessenger.SmartMessengerMIDlet
ch.ethz.jadabs.jxme.hostname: Buggy Phone
log4j.priority: DEBUG
ch.ethz.jadabs.jxme.bt.rendezvouspeer: false
ch.ethz.jadabs.mservices.smsgateway.emailsuffix: sms.switch.ch
ch.ethz.jadabs.mservices.smsgateway.senderaddress: torvalds@transmeta.com</source>

	<p>The last five lines are application properties that can be edited. 
      <b>Note:</b> This changes are lost as soon as the MIDlet-suite is 
      rebuilt by Maven. In order to permanently change the setting edit the 
      <code>midlets.xml</code> file, that is processed by the 
      <a href="http://wlab.ethz.ch/plugins/maven-antenna/">Maven-Antenna-Plugin</a>. 
      The corresponding section of the <code>midlets.xml</code> is: </p>
      
<source><![CDATA[<attributes>
  <attribute name="ch.ethz.jadabs.jxme.hostname" 
             value="Buggy Phone"/>
  <attribute name="log4j.priority" 
             value="DEBUG"/>
  <attribute name="ch.ethz.jadabs.jxme.bt.rendezvouspeer" 
             value="false"/>
  <attribute name="ch.ethz.jadabs.mservices.smsgateway.emailsuffix" 
             value="sms.switch.ch"/>
  <attribute name="ch.ethz.jadabs.mservices.smsgateway.senderaddress" 
             value="torvalds@transmeta"/>      
</attributes>]]></source>      
   </subsection>      

	<a name="manual"></a>
   <subsection name="Short Manual">
      <ol>
         <li>Start the Knopflerfish environment on the <i>infrastructure node</i> (e.g.
            a notebook) that has access to the SMTP-Server. For the configuration
            of the SMTP-Gateway service see the the documentation in 
            <a href="http://wlab.ethz.ch/jadabs/">Jadabs</a>.
<source>$ cd bt-smtp
$ sh start.sh </source></li>
              
         <li>Start the Smart Messenger MIDlet on the smart phone. Allow the 
            Smart Messenger to use the Bluetooth interface, by pressing 
            Yes when asked. Select <i>Log</i> to display the Logger view.</li>         
         <li>Wait until the two peers meet each other, i.e. until a connection is
            added. This can be seen from a log entry similar to:
<source>new connection of 000F3D4BEE8D
Waiting for connections.</source>           </li>         
         <li>Wait until the SMS-Gateway service has discovered the SMTP-Gateway 
            on the infrastructure node. 
<source>DISCOVERY_REPLY_MESSAGE received, SMTPGateway is available.</source>            </li>
         <li>Press <i>Back</i> to leave the Logger screen and return to the 
            "Settings" screen. Enter the phone number the short message has 
            to be sent to e.g. 0791234567.</li>
         <li>Press <i>Message</i> and enter the text for the short message.</li>                           
         <li>Press <i>Send</i> to send the short message via SMS-Gateway.</li>
		</ol>
      
      <p>If step 1 is omitted, the Smart Messenger will send the short message
         using the .  <b>Note</b> this might be expensive, so don't be surprised
         when you receive your monthly phone bill ;-) . </p>
   </subsection>      
   
	<subsection name="Building the MIDlet-suite">
      <p>The Smart-Messenger MIDlet-suite can be built by the Maven default goal from
         the <code>smartmessenger</code> directory:</p>
         
<source>$ pwd
.../smartmessenger

$ maven
...</source>         

	<p>This creates the <code>smartmessenger.jad</code> (Java Application Descriptor) 
      and the <code>smartmessenger.jar</code> (Java Archive) in the <code>target</code>
      directory of <code>smartmessenger</code> sub-project directory. These two 
      files can then be downloaded to the mobile phone. Note: That on the Nokia 6600
      and the Sony-Ericsson P900 both files can be installed by selecting them 
      in the Symbian Messaging Application. However <b>never</b> select the 
      JAR file! <b>Always</b> use the JAD file. Since the JAD file contains important 
      Application properties that are used to configure the bundles such as
      (BT transport, Log4J, SMS-Gateway, etc.). These properties are only listed 
      in the JAD file. By selecting the JAD file these properties are also installed
      along the the content from the JAR. However if only the JAR is selected only 
      the content of the JAR is installed, thus the important properties are missing
      and the application cannot be used at all!
      Maven repository. 
   </p>         
	 </subsection>      
   </section>   
  </body>
</document>
