<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>



<document>

  <properties>
    <title>SIP</title>
    <author email=""></author>
  </properties>
  
  <body>
    <section name="SIP">
    <subsection name="Introduction">
    	<p>
    	SIP, session initiation protocol is a protocol used for session initiation and signaling.
    	SIP is mainly used for voice-over-ip signaling, but there are extensions which make it usable for instant messenging (SIMPLE).
    	SIP can work with or without proxy. In our messenger, the proxy mainly works as a presence server, which notifies
    	clients of changes in their user lists. If you send a message to an offline user, it's automatically forwarded 
    	to a SMS or a SMTP gateway. To be able to use the services the proxy provides, a client must be successfully registered
    	and authenticated.
    	</p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="SIMPLE example">
    	<img src="images/LabOverview2.jpg"/>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="Presence server">
    	<p>
    	The proxy has a list of all users' status. Everytime a client changes its status, ha must publish it to the proxy, which forwards it to
    	all its "subscribers". It then works following the subscriber/notifier pattern. A client wishing to be notified of another user's status
    	must first subscribe to this client. The proxy also keeps a list of every notifier/subscriber pair, so when it receives a status change "publish", 
    	he simply forwards it to every subscriber.
    	</p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="Implementation">
    	<p>
    	The message types that must be supported by our messenger are :
    	</p>
    	<ul>
    		<li>REGISTER: used to register to a SIP proxy</li>
    		<li>MESSAGE: sent an instant message to the proxy, which forwards it to the corresponding client</li>
    		<li>PUBLISH: sent by a client to the proxy to publish its state, can be "online", "offline" for now nothing more is implemented</li>
    		<li>SUBSCRIBE: sent by a client to the proxy to subscribe to another user's status</li>
    		<li>NOTIFY: sent by the proxy to all the clients which are subscribed to somebody's state</li>
    		<li>INVITE: initiates a dialog session between 2 end-users, needed for compatibility reasons with MSN Messenger. The INVITE message is 
    		used along with SDP, the session description protocol, which contains what a client is capable of (in case of a voice-over-ip connection,
    		it would be the port and audio codec for the voice connection)</li>
    	</ul>
    	<p>
    		Package <code>ch.ethz.jadabs.sip.handler</code> contains an sip stack and everything needed to handle and send the messages correctly.
    		The class IMUserAgent is an abstract class which must be extended to have a complete working SIP stack. It is used by the SIP messenger
    		and both gateways.
    	</p>
    </subsection>
  
  	<subsection name="SIP Authentication">
  		<p>
  		SIP Authentication works as follow, based on a challenge-response mechanism:
  		</p>
  		
  		<ol>
  			<li>The client sends a message to the proxy.</li>
  			<li>Proxy generates a challenge, which is then send back to the client.</li>
  			<li>Client encrypts the challenge with its password and send it back to the client.</li>
  			<li>Proxy does the same and sees if it matches.</li>
  		</ol>
  	</subsection>
    </section>
  </body>

</document>
