<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
/* This is the Documentation of the SMTP-Gateway component. 
 * Rene Mueller, 2004-10-15
 * Semester work: JXME-Bluetooth for a Mobile Phone (J2ME/CLDC)
 */
 -->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Goals</title>
    <author email="muellren@student.ethz.ch">René Müller</author>
  </properties>

	<body>
  	<section name="Jadabs-CLDC Goals">
		<p>
			Jadabs-CLDC was developed during the semester work 
         <i>JXME-Bluetooth for a Mobile Phone (J2ME/CLDC)</i>
         by René Müller at the <a href="http://www.iks.inf.ethz.ch"></a>Information 
         and Communication System Group of the 
         <a href="http://www.ethz.ch">Swiss Federal Institute of Technology (ETH) Zurich</a>.
		</p>
      
      <p>Last year the number of GSM subscribers passed the 1 billion mark 
         (<a href="http://www.3gsmworldcongress.com/2005/default.asp">3GSM World congress</a>). 
         If only a small percentage of the mobile phones equipped with a enough
         processing power and memory to execute small-footprint applications there is 
         a tremendous number of such called <i>smart phones</i> already in use. The 
         number on can think of is countless. However the number of applications
         is still very low. Possible reasons are that the infrastructures require
         large investments and since the mobile technology belongs to the fastest advancing
         Information Technology the revenue cannot immediately be foreseen. Therefore
         many company still hesitate to invest in this technology.                   
      </p>
      
      <p>A solution that circumvents the necessity of having a very expensive 
         infrastructure (such as a managed network with a global coverage such as
         GSM) is to build <i>Ad-hoc networks</i>. Today even most of the mid-end
         mobile phones are equipped with a <a href="http://www.bluetooth.org">Bluetooth</a> interface.
         Bluetooth can be used to build Ad-hoc networks not only between
         mobile phones but also devices of different type. In the future device 
         vendors may also increase the support of <i>scatternets</i> which are a collections
         of Bluetooth networks that are connected together. Messages in scatternets
         have to routed over more than one station (hop). The advantage of Bluetooth is 
         that there is no infrastructure needed, the networks are created ad-hoc. Therefore
         Bluetooth communication is free. It is thus advisable that devices equipped with
         Bluetooth interfaces can exchange information.          
       </p>
       
       <p>As the devices are mobile the environment changes often. The the devices
         have to be adapted as they are moved around. New services or application 
         should be automatically installed when a device is brought into a new
         environments. For example when mobile phone is brought into a building 
         an information system application is automatically installed on the device.
         The owner can use this applications two query the in-house information system.
         As soon as the user leaves the building the application is no longer required 
         and is automatically removed. Todays mobile phones cannot be extended except 
         with simple games or ring tones. </p>
      
      <p>The Jadabs system allows that component bundles can be dynamically 
         installed and started. <a href="http://wlab.ethz.ch/jadabs">Jadabs</a> is a 
         dynamic lightweight container for small devices. Combined with the JXME messaging
         system it can be used to build applications and service for a dynamical 
         environment as described above. JXME messaging uses a messaging format 
         that is compatible to <a href="http://spec.jxta.org/nonav/v1.0/docbook/JXTAProtocols.html">JXTA</a>.
         JXME provides a uniform messaging in a heterogeneous network. 
      </p>
      
      <p>Jadabs and JXME was developed by Andreas Frei from the ETH Zurich. 
         JXME allows the use of various technology adaptors: </p>
<img src="images/jadabsoverview.jpg"/>

		<p>JXME provides a uniform messaging system on top of different 
         communication technologies. A technology is bound to JXME over 
         a <i>transport layer</i>. TCP and UDP transports are already available.
         In the semester work a <i>Bluetooth transport layer</i>
         had to be implemented allowing Bluetooth devices to use JXME.</p>
         
      <p>The original Jadabs version cannot be run on CLDC/MIDP because of the
         limitations imposed by CLDC (connected limited device configuration). 
         There is no reflection and no dynamic class loading. During the 
         semester work JXME was ported to CLDC/MIDP and a concept was 
         developed for porting Jadabs to CLDC/MIDP. </p>
      
  	</section>
	</body>
</document>
