<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
/* This is the Documentation of the SMTP-Gateway component. 
 * Rene Mueller, 2004-10-15
 * Semester work: JXME-Bluetooth for a Mobile Phone (J2ME/CLDC)
 */
 -->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>CLDC/MIDP Applications</title>
    <author email="muellren@student.ethz.ch">René Müller</author>
  </properties>

<body>
	
	<section name="CLDC/MIDP Applications">
  	
   <p>In J2SE the Knopflerfish OSGi container can dynamically install
      start and stop bundle components. Using reflection and different
      class loaders the the components can be dynamically wired. On
      CLDC/MIDP this is not possible since the CLDC imposes severe
      restrictions to things are different...</p>
      
	<p>Since there is no reflection and no class loader API components 
      cannot be injected into a MIDlet or MIDlet-suite once it is 
      installed. Moreover before installing the class files 
      have to be preverified because the code verification
      capabilities of CLDC-JVM are very limited. Therefore the 
      class files have to be preverified "offline" before 
      installing. </p>      
      
<img src="../images/components.jpg"/>

	<p>All component bundles that are required have to be merged 
      together with the OSGi container classes
      into one single archive which is then processed by the
      preverification tool. </p>

<img src="../images/bundlemidlet.jpg"/>   

	<p>This done by collecting all bundle archive the MIDlet
      has a dependency to. Then the content of these
      bundles are extracted into a single directory. Next
      a jar archive is build from the this directory which
      then will be previerified.</p>
      
    <p>Note that since there is only one class space, i.e.
      class loader per MIDlet suite. The package names
      of the the component classes and interfaces are
      no longer separated, as this is the case for Knopflerfish
      J2EE Beans, or MBeans. Class names in fact can collide, which
      results in unpredictable runtime errors.</p>
      
    <p>The differences between component bundles and the 
      components that are merged together in a MIDlet-suite
      is similar to the concept of Kernel-Modules in Linux.
      Either a feature can be compiled as kernel module, which
      can dynamically be loaded into and unloaded from
      the kernel or it can directly be compiled into
      the kernel image (monolith). </p>
   </section>  	   	
 	</body>
</document>