<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
/* This is the Documentation of the SMTP-Gateway component. 
 * Rene Mueller, 2004-10-15
 * Semester work: JXME-Bluetooth for a Mobile Phone (J2ME/CLDC)
 */
 -->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Smart SMS Gateway</title>
    <author email="muellren@student.ethz.ch">René Müller</author>
  </properties>

<body>
	
	<section name="Smart SMS Gateway">
      
  		<p>The SMS Gateway can be used to send short messages. Why is
         there an a smart SMS Gateway service necessary since sending
         short messages is nothing extraordinary on mobile phones?
         The answer is that this service is smart in sense that 
         it adapts according to the environment. It is considered
         as an example service for adaptive software components 
         on smart phones. The SMS Service either uses the GSM
         network to send the short message using the 
         <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/wma">Java Wireless Messaging API (WMA)</a> or it 
         uses an Mail-to-SMS-Gateway server when it is in communication range with
         another device that provides access to an SMTP-Gateway. Usually using an
         Mail-to-SMS-Gateway (SMTP-SMS-Gateway) is less expensive than sending the 
         short message over a GSM network. However it the device is no longer in communication range 
         with an SMTP-Gateway the SMS-Gateway transparently switches back and uses the 
         expensive GSM network. This all happens completely transparently for
         the user. The user does have to reconfigure the device. </p>
        
       <p>An architecture overview is depicted in the figure below:</p>
<img src="../multiproject/smsgateway/images/smsgatewayoverview.jpg" />       
        
       <p>The <a href="../multiproject/smsgateway/index.html">SMS-Gateway</a> that provides service uses the 
         <a href="../multiproject/smsservice/index.html">SMS-Service</a> that sends the short message
         using WMA (dashed arrows in figure). In order to send an email to the SMTP-SMS-Gateway
         JXME messaging with the <a href="../multiproject/jxme-bt-j2me/index.html">JXME BT Transport</a> is used 
         to connect to the infrastructure host that is equipped with a network interface and 
         a BT interface and  has access to an SMTP-Gateway. Furthermore it must also have
         a JXME message service and a BT transport layer. Additionally an SMTP-Gateway service must
         be available on the infrastructure host that can be used to send the email to the 
         SMTP-SMS-Gateway. This path is shown in figure with solid arrows. </p>
         
         <p>For a detail description see the 
            <a href="../multiproject/smsgateway/index.html">documentation of SMS Gateway</a>.</p>
   </section>  	   	
 	</body>
</document>