<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
/*
 * 
 */
 -->
 
 <document>
  <properties>
    <title>Jadabs Changes</title>
    <author email="frei@inf.ethz.ch">Andreas Frei</author>
  </properties>
  <body>

    <section name="News and Status">
      <p>
        This document contains the latest news and status regarding the
        Jadabs project.
      </p>    
    </section>
    
    <release version="0.7.1" date="2004-11-25" description="fixes, PPC-gui">
		<action dev="andfrei" type="add">
      		Several fixes for RemoteFW, a PocketPC-GUI version, notification
      		for appearing and disappearing nodes.
      	</action>
      	<action dev="andfrei" type="add">
      		Added startup script for j9 on PocketPC.
      	</action>
    </release>
    
    <release version="0.7.0" date="2004-11-08" description="released to open source">
		<action dev="andfrei" type="add">
      		We released this project to the open source community hosted by
      		berliOS.de. Any improvements and suggestions are welcome!
      	</action>
    </release>
    
    <release version="0.6.8" date="2004-11-03" description="remotefw,startup,docu">
		<action dev="andfrei" type="update">
      		RemoteFramework has been again implemented with the PeerNetworkService.
      	</action>
		<action dev="andfrei" type="update">
      		The startup scripts have been adapted for an easier start.
      	</action>
      	<action dev="andfrei" type="update">
      		The documentation has been improved but we are still a bit behind ;-)
      	</action>
    </release>
    
    <release version="0.6.7" date="2004-10-19" description="jxme.jxta.org integration">
		<action dev="andfrei" type="update">
      		The JXTA/JXME project has been integrated as new messaging layer.
      		Instead of one jxme package, the services have been taken out and
      		packaged seperately from the core messaging. 
      	</action>
		<action dev="andfrei" type="">
      		Following packages have not yet been ported to new jxme service layer:
      		eventsystem, remoteframework.
      	</action>
    </release>
    
    <release version="0.6.6" date="2004-07-09" description="Prose integration, Stargate">
		<action dev="andfrei" type="add">
      		Integrated Prose-1.2.1 into a new distribution. This allows now
      		to run full dynamic runtime AOP on normal VMs combined with
      		the already included AspectJ and Nanning.
      	</action>
		<action dev="andfrei" type="add">
      		Stargate is a High-End Sensorboard used to coordinate sensors in its
      		range with desktop machines. We successfully tested Jadabs on this
      		board for following components: jxme-udp, jxme-tcp, eventsystem, nanning.
      	</action>
    </release>
    
    <release version="0.6.5" date="2004-06-17" description="Jadabs-MainGui, remotefw, shell">
		<action dev="andfrei" type="update">
      		Changed package name for eventsystem.svc to eventsystem.impl.
      		New policy is not to use "I" anymore infront of the interfaces
      		as the interfaces should be anyway in a api package.
      	</action>
		<action dev="andfrei" type="update">
      		Moved Jadabs site to our new URL http://wlab.ethz.ch/jadabs
      	</action>
      	<action dev="andfrei" type="update">
      		Thirdparty packages for osgi should now have all -osgi suffix.
      	</action>
      	<action dev="dullerm" type="add">
      		Created a bundle for log4j to get one instance for whole
      		OSGi container.
      	</action>
      	<action dev="andfrei" type="add">
      		Generated an SWT bundle for win32, linux.
      	</action>
    	<action dev="andfrei" type="fix">
      		JaclDiscovery layer had some minor bugs. Work now with offsets
      		from remote machines.
      	</action>
    	<action dev="andfrei" type="add">
      		The Jadabs-MainGUI has been added. Remote Peers can be be controlled
      		over this GUI to start/stop/install/uninstall bundles remotely.
      	</action>
      	<action dev="rjan" type="shell">
      		Shell has been adapted to the new remoteframework and extended 
      		with a plugin mechanism for new commands.
      	</action>
      	<action dev="andfrei" type="update">
      		The RemoteFramework has been adapted to fit the needs for a
      		a active and reactive remoteframework.
      	</action>
    </release>
        
    <release version="0.6.4" date="2004-06-04" description="AOP-Extension, Documentation">
      <action dev="andfrei" type="add">
      	Jadabs has been extended with the possibilty to use dynamic AOP and
      	AspectJ, see the Jadabs-AOP site for fourther information.
      </action>
      <action dev="andfrei" type="add">
      	A new subproject has been added to integrate OSGi and Nanning.
      </action>
      <action dev="rjan" type="fix">
      	Some fixes in the remote framework and discovery mechanism.
      </action>
      <action dev="andfrei" type="update">
      	Documentation has been extended to reflect the AOP changes and related
      	work/projects.
      </action>
    </release>
    
    <release version="0.6.3" date="2004-05-22" description="added services for RemoteFramework and discovery">
      <action dev="andfrei, rjan" type="add">
      	We added some testing code for a RemoteFramework which will take use
      	of a discovery service.
      </action>
      <action dev="rjan" type="add">
      	Jacl will get a new discovery service inside the eventsystem. It
      	is quite similar to Jini concept but works on top of the Jxme layer.
      	Once we have sorted out its functionality it should get an independent
      	bundle.
      </action>
    </release>
    
    <release version="0.6.0" date="2004-04-08" description="move to OSGi">
      <action dev="andfrei" type="update">
      	With this new release we moved to the OSGi standard. The Jadabs-core
      	is superseded by the OSGi-API and <a href="http://www.knopflerfish.org/">Knopfelfish</a>
      	implementation. All further development will take usage of the OSGi-API. The
      	messaging-layer and the eventsystem have been transformed onto
      	the new API.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.5.1" date="2004-04-02" description="bugfixes and new shell component">
      <action dev="andfrei" type="fix">
      	Some bugfixes concerning windows/linux platforms.
      </action>
      <action dev="andfrei" type="add">
        Jadabs-Shell component to control the runtime components.
      </action>           
    </release>
    
    <release version="0.5.0" date="2004-03-29" description="first public release">
      <action dev="andfrei" type="update">
      	EventSystem will be bound to the UDPPeerNetwork. This will be
      	changed at a later stage to dynamic PeerNetwork bynding.
      </action>              
    </release>

<!--    <release version="1.0" date="2003-06-05">
      <action dev="vmassol" type="add">
        Added blah blah.
      </action>              
      <action dev="vmassol" type="fix">
        Corrected bug blah blah.
      </action>              
      <action dev="vmassol" type="remove">
        Removed blah blah.
      </action>              
    </release>
-->

  </body>
</document>
