<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
/*
 * 
 */
 -->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Jadabs Applications</title>
    <author email="frei@inf.ethz.ch">Andreas Frei</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Jadabs Applications">
      <p>
        This document shows the application of Jadabs and its services.
      </p>


      <subsection name="Overview of the Projects">
        <table>
          <tr><th>Document</th><th>Description</th></tr>
          
          <tr><td><a href="#Mindstorms-Robots">Mindstorms Robots</a></td>
            <td>
							The well known Lego-Mindstorms have also found an
							application in our research. As a basis the robots are independent
							vehicles. By adding new services or changing service
							the robots can be adapted to perform more logic espacially
							when more robots are in their communication range and
							coordination is needed.
            </td>
          </tr>
          
          <tr><td><a href="#Multi-Homing">Multi-Homing Lab</a></td>
            <td>
							A device like a PDA or mobile phone has already at
							least two communication possibilities like Wireless Lan,
							Bluetooth, GMS, infrared, etc. The problem is now that
							once one communication does not work we can not just 
							switch to another one. We need to setup new connections
							and maybe we can't even use the same connection layer like
							IP. By changing the configuration and reconfiguring the environment
							of such devices dynamically	we are able to keep connections
							open on higher layers.
            </td>
          </tr>
          
          <tr><td><a href="#Former-Labs">Former-Labs</a></td>
            <td>
							We have given these projects as laboratory assignments
							to many groups.
            </td>
          </tr>
          

        </table>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    
       <section name="Mindstorms-Robots">
     <p>
			In the Mindstorms Lab students get several robots built 
			out of Lego Mindstorms kit. The robot contains an iPAQ 
			as its brain to allow autonomous movements. As such the 
			robot can be started to fullfill a basic task, for example 
			moving randomly a grid. 
		</p>
		<p>
			The goal of this lab is to extend the robot with new 
			behaviour without to restart the whole robot application. 
			Image two robots are moving on this grid and you want to 
			connect that one robot follows the other. The second robot 
			would therefore get a slave extension which allways copies 
			the movements from the master robot. Jadabs allows to put 
			new extensions into the system. By using Prose, a dynamic 
			AOP system, it is also possible to crosscut the running 
			application at different points to execute specific 
			additional behaviour.
     </p>
		<img src="robotsellipsepicture.jpg" alt="Mindstorms Robot"/>
		
  </section>
    
  <section name="Multi-Homing">
		<p>
			During the PDA Bluetooth/WLan lab students use the Jadabs
			framework to switch from Bluetooth to Wireless connections,
			depending on the common sense. The students have to explore 
			the possibilities of this framework and to write an application. 
			An application has to detect the other PDAs, and upload extensions 
			to the other PDAs to get a common layer of knowledge, like using 
			Bluetooth for all or using one node as a bridge between the two 
			different infrastructurs.
     </p>
		</section>
    
    <section name="Former-Labs">
		<table>
			<tr>
				<th>Lab</th>
				<th>Students</th>
				<th>Documentation</th>
			</tr>
			
			<tr>
				<td>Robots SS 2004</td>
				<td>
					Michael Duller, René Müller, Jan S. Rellermeyer, Mario Tadey

				</td>
				<th><a href="http://wlab.ethz.ch/robots">website</a>, <a href="http://wlab.ethz.ch/robots/ara.pdf">pdf</a></th>
			</tr>
			
			<tr>
				<td>Multihoming WS 03/04</td>
				<td>
					Marc Kramis, Roland Schuler
				</td>
				<th><a href="http://www.iks.inf.ethz.ch/sda/labor/docs/multihomingWS0304.pdf">Documentation</a></th>
			</tr>
			
			<tr>
				<td>Robots WS 03/04</td>
				<td>
					Oliver Deak, Philipp Bolliger
				</td>
				<th><a href="http://www.iks.inf.ethz.ch/sda/labor/docs/robotsWS0304.pdf">Documentation</a></th>
			</tr>

			<tr>
				<td>Robots (A): SS 2003</td>
				<td>
					Hannes Geissbuehler, Manuel Graber, Andrea Weisskopf,
					Nicole Hatt, Luzius Meisser
				</td>
				<th><a href="http://www.iks.inf.ethz.ch/sda/labor/docs/BotGrASS03.pdf">Documentation</a></th>
			</tr>
			
			<tr>
				<td>Robots (B): SS 2003</td>
				<td>
					Vito Piraino, Kien Hung Ong, Christoph Pluess, Hao Zhou, 
					Slavisa Maslic
				</td>
				<th><a href="http://www.iks.inf.ethz.ch/sda/labor/docs/BotGrBSS03.pdf">Documentation</a></th>
			</tr>
			
		</table>
	</section>
    
 </body>
</document>
